<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>thedeep3nd</title>
    <link href="https://thedeep3nd.io/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://thedeep3nd.io" />
    <updated>2018-10-26T19:59:29-04:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>siddharth</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://thedeep3nd.io</id>

    <entry>
        <title>fun with DNS</title>
        <author>
            <name>siddharth</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://thedeep3nd.io/fun-with-dns/"/>
        <id>https://thedeep3nd.io/fun-with-dns/</id>

        <updated>2018-10-26T19:59:10-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://thedeep3nd.io/media/posts/2/" alt="" />
                    or working through minor issues w/ publii/gh-pages/namecheapnamecheap needs DNS records which point&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://thedeep3nd.io/media/posts/2/" alt="" />
                <h4><span  >or</span> <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><em>working through minor issues w/ publii/gh-pages/namecheap</em></span></h4>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">namecheap needs DNS records which point to gh-pages' IP addresses. </span></p>
<p>This needs to be updated through Namecheap (in the domain 'control panel'), keeping in mind that they aren't hosting anything. That is left up to the user; options are to either:</p>
<ul>
<li>maintain a physical server which will directly host the site</li>
<li>use a hosting service such as Wordpress (paid) or Github Pages/Gitlab Pages (free)</li>
</ul>
<p>My setup: <em>gh-pages</em> is the name of my Github repository. When a change gets pushed to the master branch, a couple things happen behind the scenes:</p>
<ol>
<li>Github Pages <em>builds</em> the project</li>
<li>Assuming a successful build, the site is then <em>deployed</em> to <code>username.github.io/gh-pages</code></li>
<li>Depending on the DNS configuration, hitting the <code>thedeep3nd.io</code> URL should show the updated site (basically a mirror of the other site).</li>
</ol>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">CNAME files</span></p>
<p><code>CNAME</code> is a top-level file in the parent directory that is used by Github Pages to handle custom domain names. Any change (modification, creation, deletion) to the C<em>ustom Domain</em> field (in repo settings) will be treated as an actual commit to repo.</p>
<p>Another relevant fact: Github Pages limits you to one site per organization (<a href="http://username.github.io/">username.github.io</a>), but does not limit the number of <em>project</em> sites you're allowed to have, ie. <a href="http://username.github.io/myoroject">username.github.io/myproject</a> is also allowed, assuming that <em>myproject</em> is a gh-pages repo.</p>
<p>However, issues can appear when:</p>
<ul style="list-style-type: circle;">
<li>Two (or more) separate gh-pages repos have the <strong>same</strong> custom domain in their CNAMEs. This is easier to fix since its a github issue, whereas:</li>
<li>your DNS records (hosted by Namecheap) are broken because of either an incorrect <em>A</em> record (mapping your domain to the Github Pages IPs</li>
</ul>
<p>In my haste to try out Publii, while I already had <a href="http://siddharth-agarwal.github.io">siddharth-agarwal.github.io</a> being published from its own repo, my new repo now also had an identical CNAME.</p>
<p>Eventally I tracked down the issue: I had added a URL redirect (?) from <a href="http://siddharth-agarwal.github.io">siddharth-agarwal.github.io</a> → <a href="http://thedeep3nd.io">thedeep3nd.io</a> <em>manually in my Namecheap settings</em>. So essentially, after a Publii commit to gh-pages, everything would break.</p>
<p>Once I deleted the CNAME record from Namecheap's DNS management system, everything started to work again.</p>
<pre><code>&gt; dig +noall +answer thedeep3nd.io
thedeep3nd.io.		1798	IN	A	185.199.111.153
thedeep3nd.io.		1798	IN	A	185.199.108.153
thedeep3nd.io.		1798	IN	A	185.199.110.153
thedeep3nd.io.		1798	IN	A	185.199.109.153

## after everything started working again ##
</code></pre>
<p>Strange issue.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>first post</title>
        <author>
            <name>siddharth</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://thedeep3nd.io/first-post/"/>
        <id>https://thedeep3nd.io/first-post/</id>
            <category term="publii"/>
            <category term="cms"/>
            <category term="blog"/>

        <updated>2018-10-25T19:01:19-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://thedeep3nd.io/media/posts/1/" alt="" />
                    Surprised at the growth in the open-source CMS space over the last&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://thedeep3nd.io/media/posts/1/" alt="" />
                <p class="align-left">Surprised at the growth in the open-source CMS space over the last couple years. It was a pretty straightforward process to get a blog up and running (with some help from <a href="https://getpublii.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Publii</a> and Github Pages). I've had this domain - <a href="thedeep3nd.io" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">thedeep3nd.io</a> - for a while now, but never got around to utiziling it - vaguely remember looking at some (closed-source) tools at the time I purchased the name but the process seemed time-consuming and involved.</p>
<p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Github Pages</span>: Big fan of the nearly seamless integration of Github Pages and Jekyll; it's nice to be able to use these kinds of tools (which saves developers hours of debugging minor bugs). With Publii handling the work of locally building the project, committing the changes to Github, and deploying, my workflow doesn't need to involve the command line at all.</p>
<p>With regard to my current setup: Github Pages is serving as the hosting service for the site (which means that behind the scenes, I have a Github repository containing the code that builds this site). A commit to this repo triggers a rebuild/redeploy of the whole site on their end. It's a bit complicated by the custom domain that I'm using, which involved creating a <code>CNAME</code> file which handles redirects/DNS stuff<em>.</em> For the most part though, Publii and gh-pages create all of the boilerplate JS/HTML/Ruby pieces necessary to link everything up. I did look into some other options - namely, Jekyll and Octopress - when deciding on a framework for the site, but Publii had a couple things that really appealed to me and eventually won me over:</p>
<ul>
<li>a desktop client for Mac</li>
<li>accessible/concise documentation</li>
<li>ability to build/preview local changes before deploying (committing) to the Github repo</li>
<li>an active and growing open-source community</li>
<li><em>free</em> to use</li>
</ul>
<p>I'm sure that it's not the most feature-rich or customizable CMS tool out there, but it seems to have pretty much everything that I want: simplicity, ease of use, and (hopefully) dependability.  </p>
<hr><address>More to come.</address>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
